<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: programming | Markus Kusano]]></title>
  <link href="http://markus-kusano.github.io/blog/categories/programming/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://markus-kusano.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-01-31T08:23:22-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://markus-kusano.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Markus Kusano]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Learning Programming]]></title>
    <link href="http://markus-kusano.github.io/blog/2014/01/03/learning-programming/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-03T10:59:18-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://markus-kusano.github.io/blog/2014/01/03/learning-programming</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A friend recently told me he wanted to learn how to program and use a
unix-like. He asked me to checkout a <a href="http://ocw.mit.edu/courses/electrical-engineering-and-computer-science/6-046j-introduction-to-algorithms-sma-5503-fall-2005/">Intro to Algorithms</a>,
an open course from MIT. I watched a video on a subject I didn&rsquo;t really know
and it was interesting. Of course it&rsquo;s a class on algorithms so it is probably
pretty high level compared to a course on embedded devices.</p>

<p>I learned how to program three or four years ago during summer break from
reddit&rsquo;s <a href="reddit.com/r/carlhprogramming">Carl H. Programming</a>. His course is
taught in C and had a decent amount of exercises. He pushed pointers and
multi-dimensional arrays from the start which was really useful, especially
once I started doing more C programming on micro-controllers. When I was using
it, the course was never finished and abruptly ended with recursive algorithms
with a tic-tac-to project. A year ago I got some closure when I programmed a
tic-tac-to board and AI (min-max) in C++.</p>

<p>This reminded me of something I read about reading literature. That it doesn&rsquo;t
really matter if you read something and understand <em>everything</em> but more
importantly that you understand something. The context was more like a kid
reading <em>Gravity&rsquo;s Rainbow</em> than a kid reading <em>Structure and Interpretation of
Computer Programs</em> but I wonder if the idea still holds weight for technical
material. For something as vast as programming, especially when your goal is
&ldquo;learn programming&rdquo; and nothing specific maybe just reading material and seeing
what sticks is the best way to do it. Will the important topics rise to the top
so that even if you miss it the first time maybe on the third or fourth you&rsquo;ll
get it?</p>

<p>At the very least, I think its good to avoid spending too much time on trying
to find the best textbook or video series to use. This probably goes for many
things other than learning; I&rsquo;ve found myself drained of energy browsing
Netflix for something to watch that I just give up. Obviously, counter
productive to entertainment.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[My Coding Setup]]></title>
    <link href="http://markus-kusano.github.io/blog/2013/12/11/my-coding-setup/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-11T18:26:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://markus-kusano.github.io/blog/2013/12/11/my-coding-setup</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>For the past three year&rsquo;s I&rsquo;ve been using Unix as my IDE for mostly C and C++
programming.</p>

<p>The two main components are Vim and ctags.</p>

<p>Vim is a text editor that uses modal hotkeys. It took a bit to learn the basics
but it keeps your fingers on the homerow for which keeps your fingers focused
on typing. There&rsquo;s a lot of somewhat esoteric hotkeys to do stuff like change
the case of a letter that seem kind of worthless, and maybe they are, but it
seems like the ones that come in handy are the ones that stick in your brain
after a while.</p>

<p>Ctags generates a database of function names and definitions found in source
files. You can run it in your project directory and it will generate file
locations of function implementations.</p>

<p>Ctags and Vim integrate together; while in Vim you can press a variety of
hotkeys to open up and jump to the location of a functions definition. This
works great for when you don&rsquo;t understand what is going on.</p>

<p>This leaves you with all the great core Unix tools to analyze, modify or create
additional source code.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
