<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: order theory | Markus Kusano]]></title>
  <link href="http://markus-kusano.github.io/blog/categories/order-theory/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://markus-kusano.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-04-16T16:37:44-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://markus-kusano.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Markus Kusano]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Partial Orders and Programming]]></title>
    <link href="http://markus-kusano.github.io/blog/2013/09/25/partial-orders-and-programming/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-25T15:42:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://markus-kusano.github.io/blog/2013/09/25/partial-orders-and-programming</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2>Order Relations</h2>

<p>Partial order relations are a fairly simple topic but it was one I initially
struggled with. Order relations are how you define ideas like greater than,
less than and equal to. If you are familiar with C++, you can think of this as
overloading the <code>&gt;</code>, <code>&lt;</code> and <code>==</code> operators for your class. We will first
discuss two order relations: total orders and partial orders and then discuss
how they are related to concurrent programming.</p>

<h3>Total Orders</h3>

<p>Total order relations are those used for natural numbers (1,2,3). This is a
fairly intuitive concept which has been taught to us all since Elementary
school. The key idea is that every natural number can be compared with every
other natural number as being greater than less than or equal.</p>

<p>However, there are some concepts in which each item can only be compared to a
subset of items; this is a partial order relation.</p>

<h3>Partial Orders</h3>

<p>Consider the following street addresses:</p>

<ol>
<li>479 Pennsylvania Ave.</li>
<li>481 Pennsylvania Ave.</li>
<li>1802 Oak Lane</li>
</ol>


<p>It makes sense to say that 479 Pennyslvania Ave. comes before 481 Pennsylvania
Ave but, what can you say about the order between 479 Pennsylvania Ave. and
1802 Oak Lane? Street addresses are examples of things that have a partial
order relation.</p>

<p>(the street address example comes from wikipedia&rsquo;s Partial Order page)</p>

<h2>Concurrent Software Testing</h2>

<p>So why is all this math useful? It turns out that concurrent programs can be
represented as partial orders instead of total orders.</p>

<p>One way to verify a concurrent program is to test all possible thread
schedules; if all of them result in a desired output then the program is
guaranteed to be safe. The problem is that this is an astronomically large
number of tests.</p>

<p>Since accesses to different memory locations do not effect each other, you only
need to test schedule orders for each memory location instead of all the
permutations of all the memory locations.</p>

<p>This concept is called partial order reduction and is a well studied solution
to the state explosion problem in concurrent software testing. However, it is
not a perfect solution since it still results in very long testing times for
large scale programs.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
