<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: llvm | Markus Kusano]]></title>
  <link href="http://markus-kusano.github.io/blog/categories/llvm/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://markus-kusano.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-04-16T16:37:44-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://markus-kusano.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Markus Kusano]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Modifying a Build System to Output LLVM IR]]></title>
    <link href="http://markus-kusano.github.io/blog/2013/09/13/modifying-a-build-system-to-output-llvm-ir/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-13T15:53:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://markus-kusano.github.io/blog/2013/09/13/modifying-a-build-system-to-output-llvm-ir</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2>Introduction</h2>

<p><a href="http://llvm.org/">LLVM</a> and its intermediate representation (IR) are quickly
becoming and de facto standard for program analysis and instrumentation. This
is a guide to modify an established build system of an application to output
LLVM IR instead of machine code. Specifically, we will outline how to output
LLVM IR for an application using
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/GNU_build_system">autotools</a>.</p>

<h2>Requirements</h2>

<p>The requirements are:</p>

<ul>
<li>The GNU gold linker with plugin support</li>
<li>The LLVMgold plugin</li>
</ul>


<p>Detailed instructions on using the LLVM GNU gold plugin can be found
<a href="http://llvm.org/docs/GoldPlugin.html">here</a>.</p>

<p>A quick summary to check if your system has support for LLVMgold:</p>

<p>Run <code>/usr/bin/ld -v</code> and check if it reports <code>GNU gold</code>. To check if you have
plugin support run <code>/usr/bin/ld -plugin</code>; if it reports <code>missing argument</code> then
you are good to go. If it reports <code>unknown option</code> you will need to install or
build a version of GNU gold that supports plugins.</p>

<p>LLVM provides
<a href="http://llvm.org/docs/GoldPlugin.html#lto-how-to-build">documentation</a>  on
building GNU gold with plugin support and LLVMgold.</p>

<h2>LLVM&rsquo;s gold Plugin</h2>

<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gold_(linker">gold</a>) is part of GNU binutils and
is a linker with support for link time optimization (LTO). LLVM provides a gold
plugin to preform LTO which inherently works by keeping source files as LLVM IR
until link time. At link time, the entire program can be observed and
optimized.</p>

<p>We&rsquo;re not so interested in the LTO aspects but rather the ability to keep files
as LLVM IR until link time. The end result is a set of &ldquo;object files&rdquo; which are
LLVM IR; If you want to make an LLVM pass on an entire program, this is a good
starting point but beyond the scope of this post.</p>

<h2>Autotools</h2>

<p>To work with autotools, we simply need to modify some environment variables to
specify options passed to <code>clang</code>.</p>

<p>If <code>clang</code> and <code>binutils</code> are not in your path, let <code>$PREFIX</code> be where they are
installed. <code>export</code> the following environment variables.</p>

<p><code>
export CC="$PREFIX/bin/clang -emit-llvm"
export CXX="$PREFIX/bin/clang++ -emit-llvm"
export AR="$PREFIX/bin/ar"
export NM="$PREFIX/bin/nm"
</code></p>

<p>If they are in your path, you simply need:</p>

<p><code>
export CC=clang -emit-llvm
export CXX=clang++ -emit-llvm
</code>
Then, simply build the program as usual. The end result should be a set of
<code>.o</code> files which are all LLVM bitcode.</p>

<p>Without the GNU gold linker and LLVMgold plugin you will get linker errors by
using <code>-emit-llvm</code>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
