<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: coq | Markus Kusano]]></title>
  <link href="http://markus-kusano.github.io/blog/categories/coq/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://markus-kusano.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-06-14T22:13:38-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://markus-kusano.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Markus Kusano]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Shades of Cheating]]></title>
    <link href="http://markus-kusano.github.io/blog/2014/01/03/cheating/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-03T09:25:13-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://markus-kusano.github.io/blog/2014/01/03/cheating</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I was always fairly willing, unless I got too lazy, to help out my friends with
their projects. I got a great deal of help myself too. But, I wonder if I did a
disservice to my friends by helping them too much on their homework. Would they
have learned more by failing? Did they actually want help or just the answer?
You can get into a sort of paranoid state if you think too much about if people
around you want honest help or want you to do their homework for you. For me,
seeing that low-grade and a big X on a returned assignment really helped me. It
showed me exactly what I didn&rsquo;t know. The solution is always really obvious
when its right in front of you; its too easy to just say, &ldquo;oh I can do that,&rdquo;
and copy it down. But I don&rsquo;t think you actual learn anything from this.</p>

<h2>What to work on</h2>

<p>One observation I&rsquo;ve had is that when it comes to finish homework there are two
categories you can focus your time in: solving the problem or finding the
solutions manual. Both of them involve spending time to finish the task at
hand. I&rsquo;ve gotten the feeling that some people would spend <em>more</em> time trying
to find the answer rather than learning how to solve the problem. There are
obvious pay-offs to finding the solution: you&rsquo;re pretty much guaranteed to get
an A (perhaps getting caught cheating too). There are obvious pay-offs to
getting an A, an employer will give you money. This idea of learning versus
solutions manual can be extended to other parts of being a student like study
for a test or store all the equations in my calculator.</p>

<p>When it comes to straight cheating, like using your phone to look up answers
during a test, the comparison doesn&rsquo;t seem to be two different areas where you
can put in your time into. Perhaps instead of time you pay the stress of
getting caught. Regardless, time spent finding a solution or just plain
cheating doesn&rsquo;t seem productive to actually learning.</p>

<p>The <em>worst</em> part is that there are people who did learn by failing. Who didn&rsquo;t
get someone else to do their homework, who didn&rsquo;t come to a group to
check answers with a blank sheet and who spent more time trying to figure out
the problems than trying to search online for the answers. It&rsquo;s fairly obvious
that failing isn&rsquo;t an encouraged way to learn in the school system. This seems
toxic since people who prioritize getting the highest grade (perhaps through
shady lanes) falsely push the average grade too high thus hurting the curve
(there&rsquo;s probably some kind of logical fallacy in here).</p>

<h2>So what?</h2>

<p>I&rsquo;m guessing that my points are something that already been beaten to death by
actual educators. &ldquo;Of course cheating doesn&rsquo;t help anyone.&rdquo; Then what do you
say to the people around you who have worked their hardest to <em>not cheat</em> and
as a result got bad grades. What do you say when the people around them are
getting job offers left and right? &ldquo;Life&rsquo;s tough&rdquo;?</p>

<p>Question&rsquo;s I have are what are some assignments that you can&rsquo;t cheat on?
One-on-one oral examinations? There&rsquo;s an obvious incentive for students to
cheat, but what is the incentive for instructors to go through hoops to make
&ldquo;un-cheatable&rdquo; assignments?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
